I found a place.
>> A place
[music]
>> like the strangely warped set design
that reflected the madness of society in
the expressionist cinema of 1920s
Germany. It's impossible to escape the
feeling that this place [music] is a
reflection of something deeper. Exactly
what this place means is harder to say,
[music]
but like a dream that lingers with you
for days, leaving you wondering why your
brain generated [music] that particular
scenario, I can't help but wonder why
this particular photo and [music] the
idea of being lost in an endless
landscape of green hallways resonated so
deeply with people that it inspired
years of internet folklore and
storytelling [music]
before eventually being adapted into
A24's biggest box office it so far.
The idea of the back rooms itself is
straightforward. You fall through a gap
in [music] reality into some kind of
parallel dimension. There you find
endless hallways with sickly green
carpet and [music] unrelenting
fluorescent lighting. All of it
constructed with a kind of [music]
infinite randomness while still feeling
hauntingly endlessly the same. In the
movie adaptation, Clark, a failed
architect, discovers the backrooms
[music] when he falls through a wall in
the basement of his struggling furniture
warehouse.
The film and much of the internet lore
details other things [music] that happen
in this space. Monsters lurk,
organizations research the novel [music]
dimension, etc. But the structure and
design of the space itself and the
feeling that this space invokes does
most of the heavy [music] lifting. These
hallways feel strangely familiar yet are
somehow alien. [music]
And it is that space that I find most
interesting and where I think most of
the interpretive value of the backrooms
lies.
>> Come on, I'll show you. It only gets
better. The back rooms, not just the
film, but Cain Parson's YouTube series,
along with the extensive internet
writing and fan art that inspired
[music] him, seems to represent one of
the first pieces of genuine internet
folklore to truly break into [music]
mainstream success. A folk tale which
expresses something about what it feels
like to live in the bizarre, [music]
uncanny, hyper reality we find ourselves
in. In my last video on why horror is
beating out every other original genre
[music] in the box office, I said that
part of why the genre is succeeding is
because of its [music] expressionist
function. That we like horror because it
helps us talk about, express, and
process societal fears and that it's
increasing in popularity because we're
in a time of increasing anxiety. So,
let's apply that lens to examining one
of the biggest [music] horror films of
the summer and maybe more significantly
one of the biggest pieces of horror lore
to emerge on the internet. And let's see
if we can uncover [music]
some of the anxieties that are expressed
through the film and that people read
into its sprawling hallways.
[music]
This isn't real. This isn't real.
>> [music]
>> Something strange has happened to humans
over the last few hundred years that I
think we've yet to fully grapple with.
Within the space of several generations,
we have effectively terraformed [music]
the planet we live on, built massive
cities that can be seen from space,
altered the climate, and constructed an
enormously complex global economy,
dramatically changing the physical
environment in which most people on the
globe live their lives. One of my
favorite documentaries, [music] Coanais
Scottsy, tells the story of our headlong
dive into this post-industrial modern
world, doing so without narration,
trying to capture not the technical
logistics [music]
or a description of the modern systems
we live inside, but what the visceral
overwhelming scale of this thing that
humans have built actually feels like.
We are so immersed in this world that
it's easy to forget that those [music]
born just a few generations ago lived in
a fundamentally different one. [music]
One that wasn't interconnected. One
where without electricity we were still
mostly bound by the rhythms of the sun.
[music] Where we had not yet faced world
war, the threat of nuclear annihilation
or seen [music] the earth from space.
And it's not just our physical
environment that has undergone this
dramatic [music] shift. It's also our
media landscape. While just a few
hundred years ago, the average piece of
media a person might have interacted
with would have looked something like
this. [music] And while even that would
have been relatively scarce, now by
comparison, we live in a fully formed
media hyper reality. Many of us spending
the majority of our waking lives
interfacing with a vast and ever growing
incomprehensible digital landscape of
effectively infinite media. In many
ways, if you take a step back and try to
see all of this for what it is, it's a
small wonder our world even functions as
well as it does, we've benefited in many
ways from the changes that have happened
over the last few centuries. But there
are cracks in the foundation and deadly
side effects. Dangers from all this
rapid change [music] that are becoming
increasingly obvious. Some of these side
effects, especially those which manifest
on a national or global scale, are easy
to notice and [music] often discussed.
But underneath all of that is what it
feels like for an individual to live
inside this brave new world of rapidly
changing
>> [music]
>> urban, suburban, and digital media
environments. I want to be clear, I'm
not saying the past [music] was
inherently better or that change hasn't
happened before. I think the unique
challenge of our current time is the
rate at which change is taking place.
While previous [music] eras might have
had multiple generations to adapt to a
major change in the technological or
media environment, [music] giving them
space to create new rituals, habits, and
social adaptations that would allow them
to maintain a [music] sense of community
and meaning within the new environment.
Now, with the technological environment
essentially changing every decade for
several hundred years, institutions,
rituals, and systems of community are
struggling to keep pace, it's difficult
for one generation to help guide the
next on how [music] to live in an
environment when each generation is
facing a new environment with a fresh
set of [music] challenges. All of this
change is affecting us personally and
psychologically. We cannot see the water
threatening to drown us, but we can feel
it.
Hello.
What is this space? What haunts the back
rooms?
[music]
>> Good evening, Mr. Torrance.
>> Good evening.
It must have been sometime in 2018, a
year before the backrooms photo emerged,
when something called vapor wave first
started appearing in my YouTube feed.
[music]
I was initially drawn in by the sound
itself. The spacey beats and ethereal
synths made for nice background music
for writing or driving around on a rainy
day. But there was also something about
this music and the art that accompanied
it which evoked a strange sensation in
me. Here was something that felt
simultaneously nostalgic and futuristic,
like I was looking back at a decaying
version of a parallel future where '90s
aesthetics and optimism had [music]
continued on uninterrupted by 9/11 or
the 2008 housing crisis.
Selected Memories from The Haunted
Ballroom, released in 1999 under the
alias The Caretaker, perhaps an early
[music] predecessor to Vapor Wave, taps
into a similar vein. It is effectively
an album of songs [music] that you could
have heard in the haunted ballroom of
The Shining Overlook Hotel.
Mark Fischer writing about the album
[music] and subsequent work from The
Caretaker uses the term haunttology to
describe [music] the strange sensation
this sonic landscape of decaying
nostalgia invokes. [music]
For Fiser, these soundscapes do not
express simple nostalgia. The music and
the listener are haunted by [music] a
future that the past believed in, but
which we no longer [music] do. In the
ballroom of the Overlook Hotel in the
1920s, there was once a celebratory
cultural optimism about the future.
But by the time Jack Torrance arrives on
the scene, not only has the heyday of
this optimism and revalry disappeared,
but so has the lavish future it once
hoped for.
[sighs]
Vapor Wave reflects this in the current
era. On one hand, it appears to be the
soundsscape of an idealistic utopic
future. And on the other, it's like
we're hearing the decaying memory of
that future. Not long after I discovered
Vapor Wave, I was intrigued to find the
algorithm showing me videos from Dan
Bell's Dead Mall series on YouTube. Here
was the literal manifestation of what
Vapor Wave seemed to capture. an image
of a bygone corporate utopia slowly
fading and decaying in front of us.
If the mall was a symbol of a kind of
commodified luxury consumerism and the
promise that the future would continue
getting brighter, more curated, and more
affordable, its decline represents more
than just the decline of the mall. It
represents a check our society wrote
which we cannot cash. We never received
the future promised by 80s and 90s
consumer [music] optimism where goods,
services, and living conditions would
continue improving while becoming more
and more affordable. Instead, while cost
of living has mounted year over year,
we've ended up with dead malls, endless
strip malls, restaurants, and apartments
that all look the same. And this
while not explicitly related to vapor
wave music and aesthetics, the back
rooms are haunted by a similar spirit.
[music]
Many of the videos in Kane Parson's
original YouTube series channel similar
aesthetic quirks to the vapor wave music
videos. Warped [music] VHS footage is
blended with optimistic elevator music,
but something feels off. The haunted
nature of the images is a little more
explicit. And when we look at the back
rooms, we're left asking, what are they
the back rooms of?
In the film, they are literally an
extension of a furniture store, at least
through this access point. It's like the
store just uh
continues. I guess
>> Clark's furniture store is expansive.
Like a mall, it promises a kind of
abundant consumerism, choice, and
comfort. A place where the consumption
of products is not just an end in and of
itself, but an experience to enjoy.
Supporting the mega retail experience is
the underlying infrastructure of the
stock room in the back, waiting to
replenish the shelves the moment they
run out, so [music] the customer never
has to even face the feeling of
scarcity. But Clark's store now sits
dormant, echoing, and customerless.
Clark,
>> just like the Overlook Hotel's ballroom,
Dan Bell's dead malls, and the spaces
evoked by vaporwave playlists. [music]
And below it all lurks a sprawling,
empty commercial landscape. A place that
feels like the spiritual backroom
[music] to every empty department store
in the many dying malls that speckle
North America. These are the [music]
empty back rooms of a vast corporate
empire. The stock rooms of a future
utopia which never came to [music] be.
an empty maze haunted by the ghost of a
better version of America that every '9s
kid optimistically dreamt of but never
saw become a reality. This feeling is
not just nostalgia for a mall or a
childish longing for the past. It's a
feeling of losing touch with a brighter
and better future of noticing your
civilization might be in a state of
decay and that we might be trapped here
in a present that goes on forever where
the future never arrives.
We must also examine the structure of
the space itself. However, it is not
just an endless empty liinal landscape
echoing with our society's lost
potential. It is also somehow built with
a terrifying aesthetic unity. Why are
the back rooms built out of these
elements specifically? [music]
Why do they feature strange
architectural bumpouts, drab carpet,
wallpaper, and structural support
columns? [music] Everything the
backrooms is made of is borrowed from
some part of our reality. The
architectural [music] detritus that
makes up the backrooms might feel
arbitrary, but there is something which
most of these features have in common.
The back rooms are on an extremely
literal level a landscape built almost
entirely out of optimized cost-saving
design elements. At first, it just looks
like a like an office building, like a
like a huge office building.
>> The drop ceiling with its [music]
incessant overhead fluorescent lighting
is not something that is built with
beauty or human flourishing in mind.
It's affordable, quick to produce,
[music] build, and maintain. The angular
geometry of the space is exactly the
kind you'd find in a haphazard remodel
job where the builder is mostly [music]
interested in quickly converting an
unlivable space into a livable one.
These are the design features of spaces
that were built not by us but for us.
Built not with our flourishing but with
convenience and affordability for those
[music] doing the building in mind. As a
society, we may have momentarily enjoyed
some of that convenience and
affordability ourselves, but it has been
disappearing for decades now. [music]
Now, we are left with a mass-produced
culture that no longer even offers the
promise upside of mass production,
affordability. [music] And we are
realizing that in our rush to create
more, more cheaply, and to grow as fast
as possible, we have excluded things
which are valuable. access [music] to
nature, quality materials that last, a
sense of history and place. But the
truly uncanny nature of this space is
that despite being built [music] out of
the design ephemera of optimization, it
seems devoid of any [music] real
purpose.
>> You you keep going and and and then you
realize that that that none of it makes
any sense.
>> Why does it exist? What is all this
endlessly optimized, affordably built
[music] space for? Perhaps this echoes a
fear that we feel about our own world
and society. That in our drive to grow,
build, and expand, we've lost sight of
what we're growing, building, or
expanding for. a fear that things in our
society are no longer being built for
humans by humans, but are instead driven
by some kind of runaway logic, one which
does not have our collective interest as
humanity in mind. And this runaway logic
is not just shaping the physical world
around us. It is also shaping the
digital landscape that surrounds us, one
we all spend an increasing amount of
time wandering through.
When I first saw the trailer for Back
Rooms in a theater, it was immediately
followed by the trailer for Exit 8. And
my first thought was, "These look like
kind of the same movie." Exit 8, a movie
based on a video game which set box
office records in [music] Japan, is
about a man who gets mysteriously stuck
in a looping underground tunnel while
trying to exit a [music] subway. The
story on the surface is pretty different
from the back rooms, but the basic
underlying feeling and ideas are pretty
similar. A character that somehow for no
apparent reason finds themselves [music]
in this mostly empty liinal space,
disconnected from reality, the sun, or
anything recognizably [music] natural or
truly human. Exit 8, also like the back
rooms, overlays this environment with a
story about a kind of [music] personal
struggle, history, and trauma. But those
elements again are [music] simply
layered on top of what generates the
actual horror which is the feeling of
drifting through a space [music]
being disconnected from time where there
is on a surface level endless [music]
variation but where it is all deep down
basically the same thing over and over
and over and over and over.
When you scroll, what are you looking
for?
I mean, I know you're looking for a
piece of content.
Maybe on the surface you want to laugh,
learn, stay informed,
but then you find that and you keep
going.
You continue looking for something.
Exit 8, unlike the back rooms, makes the
connection between the endless liinal
dimension and our digital hyper reality
explicitly.
But I think both provide an avenue for
exploring the feeling of spending a lot
of time online, of having much of your
reality defined by and shaped by digital
media. There is a school of media
criticism called media ecology. Media
ecologists posit that to really
understand media, we should think about
the media we consume not as individual
pieces of content and their messages,
but as an ecosystem or environment.
This environment, like any environment
you enter into, shapes your behavior and
has an effect on you. In the same way
you're more likely to drive instead of
walk if there's a busy road and no
sidewalk, the design of a digital
landscape affects how we interact with
it. Nobody's literally forcing you to
drive instead of walk here, but the
entire design principle of the space
encourages it. Nobody is literally
forcing you to keep scrolling until past
midnight or to watch the most
sensational attentiongrabbing content
possible. But when the entire structure
of the environment is built around that,
it's kind of hard to avoid.
The design of our digital environments
don't just influence our behavior. They
can shape our psychology, beliefs, and
emotions. Consider the structure of
social media. The constant flipping
between different ideas from place to
place. The whiplash between content that
evokes competing feelings. Seeing things
we like, desire, and fear all in the
same place. This can leave us feeling
untethered from time and space. It has a
liinal quality to it and can leave us
lost in a strange, surreal environment
where we're never sure what's around the
next corner. Sometimes you might find an
anomaly, something that feels different,
[music] unique, fresh, or out of place,
but then it keeps going. [music] You
keep going.
Eventually, you realize you hardly
remember the video you watched before
this one. You can't even recall what the
video before that was [music] about.
What posts or videos did you like last
week or a year ago? There doesn't seem
to be a bottom. It's endless. A world of
infinite variety, but where it all
somehow ends up feeling the same. What
is down here? What is it all for?
Backrooms is a film made in 2026 by Cain
Parsons, a director who is himself a
child of the internet age. The Backrooms
are a piece of internet folklore. Like
any good myth or folk legend, it has no
single authoral voice. It emerges out of
the collective unconscious and compels
almost endless interpretations. But this
is part of how any folklore functions.
Myths are a bit like society having a
collective dream. They are bizarre and
usually don't make complete sense, but
there's something about them we find
fascinating and their real value emerges
when we consider what they mean to us.
What I find most interesting is that
this landscape for some reason helped a
group of people to express or illustrate
a feeling that was already there. A
complicated feeling, one that is
difficult to put into words. And the
multitude of interpretations are not a
sign that the myth itself is meaningless
or that any of the interpretations are
wrong. They're a sign that we need art
to express the meaning found there
because the words are failing us. And
maybe the words are failing us because
we're facing something new, something
strange, our own particular flavor of an
empire in decay. the reality of coming
face to face with a society operating on
a runaway logic, generating more and
more of itself while losing sight of who
it is generating more for. And when we
realize all this, are we willing to try
to change? Or is the real horror that
maybe
>> I like it in here?
Of course, the back rooms aren't the
first or only works to explore anxiety
about the modern world using this kind
of visual language. I've already
mentioned The Shining, which explores
haunty through the liinal emptiness of
the Overlook Hotel. In an episode of The
Twilight Zone entitled Little Girl Lost,
parents search for their daughter, who
has seemingly fallen into some kind of
parallel dimension. These works like the
back rooms and exit 8 all tap into a
fear of being trapped in some kind of
world that is layered on top of our own,
expressing our fear that there is a
hyper reality around us which we cannot
see but which is encroaching on us. The
first episode of Captain Midnight's
series Showrunners explores the social
issues that are reflected in the
Twilight Zone made by showrunner Rod
Serling. The episode dives into how
Serling used the show as thinly veiled
cultural commentary, expressing views
that were important to him while dodging
censorship. I highly recommend the
episode, but the rest of the series is
great as well, [music] with each episode
diving into one of our great television
showrunners, the history and
circumstances that shape their work, and
how they approach their art. Episode two
is about my favorite showrunner, Vince
Gilligan, and you can watch all three
episodes exclusively on Nebula. [music]
Nebula is a streaming service built and
owned by creators. You won't just find
original series like Captain Midnight's
Showrunners or Sarah Davis Baker's
series Half- Remembered, which explores
those pieces of incredibly weird media
you vaguely remember from your [music]
childhood. You'll also find early access
to all of my videos along with exclusive
[music] essays from me, like my
bookshelf tour, my full-length essay on
the ethics of depicting suffering in
film, or a video where I cut together
Doom part one and two into a single film
and give it my [music] review. When you
sign up for Nebula, you'll get all of
this. The rapidly growing catalog of
exclusives, the early access to all of
my new videos without any ads or
sponsorships, and without having to dig
through a bottomless feed [music]
designed to do everything possible to
keep you hooked so it can show you more
ads. I'm always excited to talk about
Nebula because it's [music]
genuinely the best way to watch my
videos. I like having my work available
for free on YouTube, [music] but I want
people to have the option of watching my
videos without having to subject
themselves to ads. [music] the algorithm
or needing to navigate a social media
platform that feels like the back rooms.
Nebula is an online platform that
[music] still feels human. And if you
like my videos, you'll find lots of
other creators over there who I know
you'll enjoy, like Captain Midnight,
Cinemastixs, [music] and Jacob Geller.
Best of all, Nebula's very affordable.
The annual plan [music] is just $30 a
year or $2.50 a month when you sign up
using my link [music] at
go.nebula.tv/toomasflight
TV/thomasflight
or using the QR code on the screen. The
people who sign up for and watch [music]
on Nebula make it possible for me to
continue making these videos. So, come
join us. If you're here, I know you'll
like it there.